[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "Determine all positive integers $n$ for which there exist positive integers $a$, $b$, and $c$ satisfying\n\\[\n2a^n + 3b^n = 4c^n.\n\\]",
        "answer": "The answer is $n=1$. When $n=1$, $(a,b,c) = (1,2,2)$ is a solution to the given equation. We claim that there are no solutions when $n \\geq 2$.",
        "contest": "Putnam2024",
        "problem_idx": "Putnam2024-A1"
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "For which real polynomials $p$ is there a real polynomial $q$ such that\n\\[\np(p(x)) - x = (p(x) - x)^2 q(x)\n\\]\nfor all real $x$?",
        "answer": "The answer is $p(x) = \\pm x+c$ for any $c \\in \\mathbb{R}$",
        "contest": "Putnam2024",
        "problem_idx": "Putnam2024-A2"
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "Let $S$ be the set of bijections\n\\[\nT \\colon \\{1,2,3\\} \\times \\{1,2,\\dots,2024\\} \\to \\{1,2,\\dots,6072\\}\n\\]\nsuch that $T(1,j) < T(2,j) < T(3,j)$ for all $j \\in \\{1,2,\\dots,2024\\}$ and $T(i,j) < T(i,j+1)$ for all $i \\in \\{1,2,3\\}$ and $j \\in \\{1,2,\\dots,2023\\}$. Do there exist $a$ and $c$ in $\\{1,2,3\\}$ and $b$ and $d$ in $\\{1,2,\\dots,2024\\}$ such that the fraction of elements $T$ in $S$ for which $T(a,b) < T(c,d)$ is at least $1/3$ and at most $2/3$?",
        "answer": "yes",
        "contest": "Putnam2024",
        "problem_idx": "Putnam2024-A3"
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "Find all primes $p > 5$ for which there exists an integer $a$ and an integer $r$ satisfying $1 \\leq r \\leq p-1$ with the following property: the sequence $1,a,a^2,\\dots,a^{p-5}$ can be rearranged to form a sequence $b_0,b_1,b_2,\\dots,b_{p-5}$ such that $b_n-b_{n-1}-r$ is divisible by $p$ for $1 \\leq n \\leq p-5$.",
        "answer": "7",
        "contest": "Putnam2024",
        "problem_idx": "Putnam2024-A4"
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "Consider a circle $\\Omega$ with radius 9 and center at the origin $(0,0)$, and a disc $\\Delta$ with radius 1 and center at $(r,0)$, where $0 \\leq r \\leq 8$. Two points $P$ and $Q$ are chosen independently and uniformly at random on $\\Omega$. Which value(s) of $r$ minimize the probability that the chord $\\overline{PQ}$ intersects $\\Delta$?",
        "answer": "We will show that $r=0$ (and no other value of $r$) minimizes the stated probability.",
        "contest": "Putnam2024",
        "problem_idx": "Putnam2024-A5"
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "Let $c_0,c_1,c_2,\\dots$ be the sequence defined so that \n\\[\n\\frac{1-3x-\\sqrt{1-14x+9x^2}}{4} = \\sum_{k=0}^\\infty c_k x^k\n\\]\nfor sufficiently small $x$. For a positive integer $n$, let $A$ be the $n$-by-$n$ matrix with $i,j$-entry $c_{i+j-1}$ for $i$ and $j$ in $\\{1,\\dots,n\\}$. Find the determinant of $A$.",
        "answer": "The determinant equals $10^{n(n-1)/2}$.",
        "contest": "Putnam2024",
        "problem_idx": "Putnam2024-A6"
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "Let $n$ and $k$ be positive integers. The square in the $i$th row and $j$th column of an $n$-by-$n$ grid contains the number $i+j-k$. For which $n$ and $k$ is it possible to select $n$ squares from the grid, no two in the same row or column, such that the numbers contained in the selected squares are exactly $1,2,\\dots,n$?",
        "answer": "This is possible if and only if $n$ is odd and $k = (n+1)/2$.",
        "contest": "Putnam2024",
        "problem_idx": "Putnam2024-B1"
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "Two convex quadrilaterals are called \\emph{partners} if they have three vertices in common and they can be labeled $ABCD$ and $ABCE$ so that $E$ is the reflection of $D$ across the perpendicular bisector of the diagonal $\\overline{AC}$. Is there an infinite sequence of convex quadrilaterals such that each quadrilateral is a partner of its successor and no two elements of the sequence are congruent?\n[A diagram has been omitted.]",
        "answer": "no",
        "contest": "Putnam2024",
        "problem_idx": "Putnam2024-B2"
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "Let $r_n$ be the $n$th smallest positive solution to $\\tan x = x$, where the argument of tangent is in radians. Prove that\n\\[\n0 < r_{n+1} - r_n - \\pi < \\frac{1}{(n^2+n)\\pi}\n\\]\nfor $n \\geq 1$.",
        "answer": "null",
        "contest": "Putnam2024",
        "problem_idx": "Putnam2024-B3"
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "Let $n$ be a positive integer. Set $a_{n,0} = 1$. For $k \\geq 0$, choose an integer $m_{n,k}$ uniformly at random from the set $\\{1,\\dots,n\\}$, and let\n\\[\na_{n,k+1} = \\begin{cases} a_{n,k} + 1, & \\mbox{if $m_{n,k} > a_{n,k};$} \\\na_{n,k}, & \\mbox{if $m_{n,k} = a_{n,k}$;} \\\na_{n,k}-1, & \\mbox{if $m_{n,k} < a_{n,k}$.}\n\\end{cases}\n\\]\nLet $E(n)$ be the expected value of $a_{n,n}$. Determine $\\lim_{n\\to \\infty} E(n)/n$.",
        "answer": "The limit equals $\\frac{1-e^{-2}}{2}$.",
        "contest": "Putnam2024",
        "problem_idx": "Putnam2024-B4"
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "Let $k$ and $m$ be positive integers. For a positive integer $n$, let $f(n)$ be the number of integer sequences $x_1,\\dots,x_k,y_1,\\dots,y_m,z$ satisfying $1 \\leq x_1 \\leq \\cdots \\leq x_k \\leq z \\leq n$ and $1 \\leq y_1 \\leq \\cdots \\leq y_m \\leq z \\leq n$. Show that $f(n)$ can be expressed as a polynomial in $n$ with nonnegative coefficients.",
        "answer": "null",
        "contest": "Putnam2024",
        "problem_idx": "Putnam2024-B5"
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "For a real number $a$, let $F_a(x) = \\sum_{n \\geq 1} n^a e^{2n} x^{n^2}$ for $0 \\leq x < 1$.\nFind a real number $c$ such that\n\\begin{align*}\n& \\lim_{x \\to 1^-} F_a(x) e^{-1/(1-x)} = 0 \\qquad \\mbox{for all $a < c$, and} \\\n& \\lim_{x \\to 1^-} F_a(x) e^{-1/(1-x)} = \\infty \\qquad \\mbox{for all $a > c$.}\n\\end{align*}",
        "answer": "The claim holds with $c=-\\frac{1}{2}$.",
        "contest": "Putnam2024",
        "problem_idx": "Putnam2024-B6"
    }
]